Partridge mss. II LMC 2987
Lilly Library
Partridge mss. II
1931-2004
Lilly Library
Partridge, Eric, 1894-1979
LMC 2987
1 Box
The Partridge mss. II, 1931-2004, consist of the autograph correspondence and press clippings of New Zealand lexicographer, Eric Partridge (1894-1979).
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchase: 2020
Biographical / Historical
Eric Partridge (1894-1979) was born February 6, 1894, in Poverty Bay, New Zealand, son of John Thomas (a farmer) and Ethel Annabella (Norris) Partridge. In 1907, the family moved to Brisbane, Australia where Partridge passed his school years graduating from the University of Queensland in 1921, after studying Classics, French and English. He received his B.Litt. (with first class honors) from Oxford University in 1923. Serving in the Australian infantry during World War I, he lived through the horror of the Gallipoli campaign in 1915. In 1925, Partridge married Agnes Dora Vye–Parmenter with whom he had one daughter, Rosemary Ethel Honeywood Mann. After teaching for two years as a university lecturer in Manchester and London, Partridge gave up a promising academic career to found the small London publishing house, Scholartis. The press was moderately successful until the Great Depression, when he was forced to take on work as a free–lance writer. He often commented that the Depression allowed him to discover his real love and talent for writing books.
Partridge wrote over forty books on the English language, including well–known works on etymology, slang, jargon, and clichés. He died on June 1, 1979 in Devon, England.
Related Materials
See the Partridge mss., also at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series: I. Correspondence (arranged alphabetically by correspondent), II. Clippings (arranged chronologically), and III. Complete Issues (arranged chronologically).
Scope and Contents
Collection consists of handwritten letters and postcards from lexicographer Eric Partridge to correspondents including Laurie Atkinson, a long-time friend of Partridge who coined the term "catch phrase" and an amateur lexicographer himself; John W. Clark, professor of English at the University of Minnesota and sometimes collaborator with Partridge on his books; Peter and Iona Opie, children's folklorists. The correspondence to Clark includes 1 large typed chart in 7 columns (Greek, Oscan, Latin, Celtic, Old Slavic, Old Teutonic, and Modern English) with a note that this is "first draft of a small part of Origins."
Collection also includes newspaper clippings and full issues of periodicals containing articles by and about Partridge.
English language; Lexicography; Slang; Partridge, Eric, 1894-1979
- Collection Information and Provenance (Box 1)
- I. Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Atkinson, Laurie, 1948-1979 (Box 1)
    - 1948-1949 (Box 1)
    - 1950-1959 (Box 1)
    - 1960-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1974 (Box 1)
    - 1975-1979 (Box 1)
  - Clark, John W., 1958-1964 (Box 1)
  - George, Daniel, 1947-1954 (Box 1)
  - Opie, Peter and Iona, 1961-1970 (Box 1)
  - Read, Allen Walker, 1974-1978 (Box 1)
  - Spelman, Ken, 1965-1974 (Box 1)
  - Steele, Alan, 1959-1972 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1931-1974 (Box 1)
- II. Clippings (Box 1)
  - About Partridge, 1964-1979 (Box 1)
  - About Partridge (photocopies) (Box 1)
  - Obituaries of Partridge, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Reviews of books by Partridge (Box 1)
    - Dictionary of Slang and Unconventional English, 1937-1987 (Box 1)
    - Origins, 1958-1966 (Box 1)
    - Dictionary of Catch Phrases, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Eric Partridge In His Own Words, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1950-1975 (Box 1)
  - "John Clark's clippings from a relative in St. Paul, 1996", 1936-1938 (Box 1)
  - Daniel George cuttings (Box 1)
  - Slang and Navy cuttings, 1949-1976 (Box 1)
  - William Blake, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Scholartis Press (photocopy and original) (Box 1)
  - By Partridge (Box 1)
  - By Partridge (photocopies) (Box 1)
- III. Complete Issues (Box 1)
  - The Spectator, 1931 (Box 1)
  - Times Literary Supplement, 1947-1948 (Box 1)
  - Times Literary Supplement, 1949-1951 (Box 1)
  - Times Literary Supplement, 1979 (Box 1)
  - The New Statesman and Nation, 1947-1950 (Box 1)
  - Leader Magazine, 1949 (Box 1)
  - The Listener, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Tomorrow, 1951 (Box 1)
  - World Digest, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Encounter, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Horizon, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Books and Bookmen, 1975-1978 (Box 1)